Good morning, מזל טוב. Mazel tov. Today's דף daf is קל"ו, kuf
lamed vav, although we are on קל"ה עמוד ב'. kuf lamed hey
amud bet. So, and we, let's start. We are at the top
of it, at the משנה. Mishnah. So let's pick up, let's re-read
the משנה Mishnah quickly. We had a whole presentation about this, but
basically what we're doing is we're moving into the area of מתנת
שכיב מרע, Matnas Sh'chiv Mei'ra, which we've discussed in passing, but the
deathbed bequest, the oral deathbed bequest that takes effect at death. And
this is a special תקנה Takana that the Rabbis established. And then,
but our משנה Mishnah focuses on the written form of that, called
a דיאטיקי, Diatiki, which is, as we heard yesterday, a, the Greek
word for a will, a written will. But that will is only
binding when it is received, meaning an oral deathbed bequest is binding
when somebody hears it. It has to be proven obviously, so you're
going to want witnesses there to prove that it was actually said.
But a, if a will is written and not handed to anybody,
then it is not yet considered to be binding. Okay, so speaking
of binding, our משנה Mishnah talks about if it was bound to
the guy's thigh. So, but it's not binding legally. מי שמת ונמצא
דיאטיקי קשורה על ירכו. Me she’meis venimtza diyatiki keshura al yireicho.
Somebody dies, and this is a common idiom, well it was by
Avraham, right? שים נא ידך תחת ירכי. Sim na yadecha tachat yireichi.
But anyway, but yeah, I mean, and certainly in the ancient East,
the hand under the thigh is a symbol of like commitment, whatever,
taking an oath. So maybe, but also the point is if there's
no question that he wrote it. Okay, there's absolutely no question he
wrote it. הרי זו אינו כלום, Harei zo eino klum, it's not
yet legally binding, it doesn't have binding force until it's handed over.
Now, זיכה לאחר, zika belacher, once he has given it over and
handed it to somebody else, בין מן היורשים בין שלא מן היורשים,
bein min hayorshim bein shelo min hayorshim, whether the person who received
it is an heir or not an heir, דבריו קיימים, devarav kayamim,
it is binding, it's legitimate, and this is the, as I said,
the written form of the מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Sh'chiv Mei'ra. The
גמרא Gemara is going to say that even if there's not a
name written in it, even if it just says I give to
you like a blank check all of my property and he hands
it over to the person who receives it. Okay, so that is
going, that will work. And this is not a שטר מתנה Shtar
Matana because it's not to be confused with a, a straight type
of a gift because a, a gift would be effective immediately. This
is effective at death. A gift would require, would require that the
שטר shtar be written in a certain way to indicate that the
receiving of the שטר shtar is a, you know, is קונה koneh
the field and so on. This is an expression of the person's
last will and testament. Okay, that's what it is and it takes
effect at death. Okay, תנו רבנן, tana rabanan, our rabbis taught. איזהו
דיאטיקי? eizehu diyatiki? What is a דיאטיקי? Diatiki? מכל שכתוב בו, mikol
shekasuv bo, anything written in it, so this is a classic like
גמרא's Gemara etymology of Greek words in Aramaic, okay? דא תהא למיקם
ולהיות. da tehei lemeikam ulehayos. This should be to be established and
to be, this is my last will and testament. Okay, ואיזו היא
מתנה? ve-eizehu matana? Now what's a gift? So this is exactly the
question: how do you distinguish between a שטר shtar that is a
will and a שטר shtar that is a שטר מתנה? shtar matana?
Because you know,
קרקע נקנית בכסף בשטר ובחזקה. karka is niknes bekeseph shtar vechazakah. So
כסף kesef we know, you pay the money. חזקה chazakah we know,
you go ahead and you make a fence or whatever it is.
What's a שטר? shtar? So all you need to do for a
שטר shtar is you have to write three magic words, okay?
שדי נתונה לך, sadi netuna lecha, and then you hand over the
שטר. shtar. What, that would be a מתנה. matana. Or שדי מכורה
לך. sadi mechura lecha. And you'd have to know which field of
course, if I only had one field, if I didn't I'd have
to specify. Okay, so it's basically an expression, a written expression of
my דעת. da'as. So that is saying I am gifting it to
you or I am selling it to you, not that this is
my last will and testament, this is what I want to happen
when I die, okay? That would be a difference. Okay, so what
would be a, איזהו מתנה? eizehu matana? כל שכתוב בו מהיום ולאחר
מיתה. kol shekasuv bo mehayom uleachar misa. If it takes effect from
today and complete after death. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
yeah, let's, right, so let's hear what the גמרא Gemara jumps in.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מהיום ולאחר מיתה הוא דהוי מתנה?
ella mehayom uleachar misa hu dehavi matana? So only a שטר shtar
that says starting today and ending at death, that's a מתנה? matana?
מעכשיו לא הוי מתנה? me'achshav lo havi matana? If it says I
am selling you my field today or giving you my field today
that's not a gift? Of course it's a gift. What do you
mean what's a gift today and so after
death? So אלא אמר אביי הכי קאמר, ela amar Abaye: Hachi ka'amar,
here's what it means.
איזהו מתנת ברי? eizehu matnas bari? What is a gift given by
a healthy person that operates in the normal sort of structures of
קניינים, kinyanim, not through this special mechanism of מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas
Sh'chiv Mei'ra, but nevertheless שהיא כמתנת שכיב מרע, she-hi kematnas sh'chiv mei'ra,
that approximates the effect of a מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Sh'chiv Mei'ra.
How could you give a gift when you're healthy that approximates the
same thing because, you know, not everybody has the luxury, I mean
whatever, of waiting until they're on their deathbed, you know, and to
go ahead and then dictating their last will and testament. People want
to take care of it ahead of time and should take care
of it ahead of time. Here's a public service announcement: anybody who
doesn't have a will, no I'm serious, like you owe it to
your family and to your kids and to whatever, go ahead, you
know, write a will, if you, you know, even just get, download
one for free off of the internet. I'm serious, like people really
need to take the responsibility
of. Sadly you don't always have that opportunity. So anyway, somebody while
they are healthy wants to set this up. And they can't use
the mechanism of מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Sh'chiv Mei-ra. So therefore, what
do they do? They give a gift while they're alive that approximates
מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Sh'chiv Mei-ra. How? It's מהיום ולאחר מיתה. Me-hayom
U'l'achar Misah. Now in what way does that approximate a מתנת שכיב
מרע? Matnas Sh'chiv Mei-ra? איזה מתנת בריא שהיא כמתנת שכיב מרע? Eizeh
Matnas Bari shehi ke-Matnas Sh'chiv Mei-ra? דלא קני אלא לאחר מיתה? D'lo
kani ela l'achar misah? That you really only want it to take
effect, you really don't want to give up your property now, you
really only want it to take effect after you die. Okay, but
so how would you structure it if you're doing it now when
you're young and vigorous and healthy? So you would write כל שכתוב
בו מהיום ולאחר מיתה, kol shekasuv bo me-hayom u'l'achar misah, today and
after I when after I and and to complete when I die.
Now what is the effect of saying that? What is so the
so the saying today works in that it's not a מתנה לאחר
מיתה matanah l'achar misah because you can't give something can't be effective
once you're already dead, then you're not in a position to give
it and it's no longer yours, it's now transferred to your heir.
So so you have to start it today. So what do well
you don't, but you have to start it, I know, we'll get
to that, but you have to start it while you're still well
and alive. So so what does the today part mean? So we're
going to find out in the next משנה Mishnah that the today
part means as of today you own the actual title to the
land, but I have the rights to benefit from it and I've
got the פירות. peiros. Okay, so that and therefore the person says
this, the person he's giving it to owns the title, so I
and the person who gifted it retains the פירות peiros for the
period that he remains alive. Then once you know so well he
can sell the פירות peiros but he can't sell the yeah one
minute. So then once he dies, okay, the ownership of the giver
of the one who gave it only was retained the פירות peiros
for the duration of his life. So as soon as he dies,
then the one who received the land now also, you know, gets
the actual פירות peiros of the land and has full benefit and
full use of it. Now the thing is, is that what you
really it's strange that this is what you're choosing to do, because
if you had asked me what you should do is you should
say your I have it all now and you're קונה koneh a
second before I die. Okay, it doesn't have right, doesn't have to
be at when I die, could be a second before I die.
And because one of the things that now if you've done is
if you've given away the title is that now I can't sell
it. Let's say the market has shot up, I can make a
killing if I sell this piece of real estate right now, I'm
afraid that if I wait I'm going to lose it or whatever.
It's much better for me to sell it now, even for better
for what I want to give to you, sell it now, get
the money, reinvest it or who knows what. Okay? I can't, I
no longer own the title. So why would you want to give
that away, right?
So so that's like strange why you would want to structure it
that way. That's point but that seems to be the classic way,
I'm giving it to you today, now title, and I retain the
פירות peiros until I die. Now another important question though is that
תוספות Tosafos addresses is can you retract it? Because as we know
by wills, right, people are always writing this is my last will
and testament until I write my next last will and testament, right?
So you're constantly that's why you have to say last because you
can people will write and revise and revise and this is my
last one, the last one that I've written as of this writing.
Okay, so that's certainly true by a מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas Sh'chiv
Mei-ra, right? The guy could be on his deathbed for a year,
you know, right? So he could have a couple of revisions. What
about מהיום ולאחר מיתה? Me-hayom U'l'achar Misah? Can you actually retract that
if it's a gift מהיום ולאחר מיתה? Me-hayom U'l'achar Misah? So if
you look at תוספות, Tosafos, let's look at תוספות, Tosafos, he says
פירוש כל שכתוב בו מהיום ולאחר מיתה, Peirush kol shekasuv bo me-hayom
u'l'achar misah, says פירוש בקונטרס דהוי כמתנת בריא שאין יכול לחזור בו.
Peirush b'kuntres de-havei ke-matnas bari she-ein yachol lachzor bo.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says actually it only the only way it's
similar is that it fully takes effect at death, but it actually
because you're giving it while you're healthy you cannot retract it. He
says וקשיא דתנן פרק קמא דבבא מציעא V'kasha d'nan perek kama d'Bava
Metzia
so he has all this evidence from another גמרא Gemara that you
can retract it. So he says so what's his answer? ומפרש רבינו
תם U'mefarsh Rabbeinu Tam it's one, two, three, six lines down in
the narrow line: ומפרש רבינו תם מהיום ולאחר מיתה היינו מהיום אם
לא אחזור בי עד לאחר מיתה ומאי רק כגון שפירש בפירוש מהיום
אם לא יחזור עד לאחר מיתה דמסתמא אם אמר מהיום ולאחר מיתה
הוי מהיום קני גופו ולאחר מיתה קני פירות U'mefarsh Rabbeinu Tam: Me-hayom
U'l'achar Misah, haynu me-hayom im lo achzor bi ad l'achar misah. U'mai
rak k'gon sheperash beferush me-hayom im lo yachzor ad l'achar misah. D'mistama
im amar me-hayom u'l'achar misah, havei me-hayom kani gufo v'l'achar misah kani
peiros etc. etc. So
what he actually does is he says the רשב"ם Rashbam is right
in principle. If you just said מהיום ולאחר מיתה, Me-hayom U'l'achar Misah,
you've gifted away the land today and you can't retract it. But
what he says, when the גמרא Gemara is talking about a מתנת
בריא Matnas Bari that approximates a מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas Sh'chiv Mei-ra,
you really would say more than the גמרא Gemara just said. If
you really wanted to have all of these sort of flexibility or
whatever as of a מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas Sh'chiv Mei-ra, you would
say מהיום... Me-hayom... מהיום אם לא אחזור בי עד לאחר מיתה Mehayom
im lo achzor bi ad l'acher mita and you explicitly retain for
yourself the right to retract it. Now why is that? Now well
no, because that's another type of a חזרה. chazarah. Meaning why that's
beneficial is I could retract it because Michael's really annoyed me and
that's it I'm writing you out of my will and I'm going
to give it to somebody else. Or I could retract it because
I realized like, hey, I've got a great opportunity to sell it
now and whatever and Michael can even get more money out of
my estate if I go ahead and I sell it. I sell
it? You, right, well we'll see that like we'll right, so that's
going to also come up in the next משנה mishna like do
you have the right to sell it or whatever. Anyway, but if
I've retained the right to retract it, I can retract it, do
what I want, and then create another מתנה. matana. Yes. Am I
misreading רבנו תם? Rabbeinu Tam? Because when he says מפרש רבנו תם
mefaresh Rabbeinu Tam עד לאחר מיתה ad l'acher mita היינו hainu
that is to say מהיום אם לא אחזור בי. mehayom im lo
achzor bi. You don't have to say it בפירוש. b'feirush. No, because
you've got to be reading the next line. ומיירי כגון שפירש בפירוש
מהיום אם לא אחזור umayri kegon shepeirash b'feirush mehayom im lo achzor
because there's a סתירה stira in different גמרות Gemorot whether you can
be חוזר chozer or not when you say מהיום ולאחר מיתה. mehayom
v'l'acher mita. So תוספות Tosafot says this גמרא Gemara that is trying
to discuss and other גמרות Gemorot that are discussing a מתנת בריא
שהיא כמתנת שכיב מרע matnat bari shehi k'matnat shchiv mera
are talking when you explicitly say you have the right to retract.
Okay. Now one could also imagine that you could do other ways
to indicate that. Let's say you wrote at the top of your
document מתנת בריא שהיא כמתנת שכיב מרע. matnat bari shehi k'matnat shchiv
mera. I am giving this to you מהיום ולאחר מיתה. mehayom v'l'acher
mita. Presumably that would also mean and I have the right to
retract. So you know, if the context is such that it's understood
to be a type of a writing of a will early and
doing it something that approximates a will, then not only does the
other guy really only get the benefit after you die, but you
retain the right to reverse it and retract it, which addresses a
lot of the issues we were discussing. Yes. Two questions. One, does
this apply both to land and to movables? Yes. Second, two floors
down there are flyers for the UJA Federation to buy an annuity
from UJA Federation. Yeah. And you get essentially the פירות. peirot. Right.
And the שול shul gets the principal when you die. So this
actually would sound like it might be similar to that. That's a
good idea. That's a nice point. Right.
It's the same exact type of a structure. Okay, except... All right,
so now let's continue. You said something before you die though, right?
You could just say, right, you could just say this is all
going to take place so second before I die. And it's interesting
why the גמרא Gemara hasn't like doesn't think that that's the most
easiest way to sort of make this take effect. I don't know.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, יתיב
רבא בר רב הונא. Yativ Rava bar Rav Huna. So רבא בר
רב הונא Rava bar Rav Huna was sitting באכסדרה b'achsadra in the
what's it like a portico, right, דבי רב d'bei Rav of the
house of רב, Rav, maybe the ישיבה yeshiva of רב, Rav, they
was out there on the porch. Okay. ויתיב וקאמר משמיה דרבי יוחנן
veyativ v'ka'amar mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan and he was sitting and saying in
the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
it's always interesting which מסכתות masechtot and which topics you have like
certain rabbis are quoted disproportionately. You know, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan plays
a very big role like in this פרק. perek. Anyway, וקאמר משמיה
דרבי יוחנן: v'ka'amar mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan: שכיב מרע שאמר כתבו ותנו מנה
לפלוני, shchiv mera she'amar kitvu u'tnu mana l'ploni,
if the person on his deathbed said write out a will for
ראובן Reuven and give him my property and give him the will,
right, and do this while I'm alive. Now remember, a will is
only effective when it's handed over. So if he would have just
said "give my property to ראובן", Reuven then ראובן Reuven would have
gotten it. That would be a verbal מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shchiv
mera. But he says, "write it out and give it to him",
so is this now a verbal מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera
that's effective immediately? Or is this a written מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat
shchiv mera, a written will that's only effective when the document is
given over? And the נפקא מינה nafka mina is that he died
before they had the time to write it and give it over.
Okay. So he says כתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני. kitvu u'tnu mana l'ploni.
So here you go, by the way, Charlie, not a piece of
land, a hundred dollars. Okay. ומת. u'meit. By the way, that's another
way in which a will is, you know, cannot be confused with
a שטר קנין. shtar kinyan. A שטר קנין shtar kinyan only works
on land. If you write in a will, "please give, you know,
my million dollars in cash to so and so", that would never
work as a שטר, shtar, right? But that totally works as a,
as a דיאתיקי, diatiki, as a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shchiv mera.
Can't you give a gift in a שטר shtar without land? Correct.
מטלטלין metaltelin is only נקנית niknet with, you know, עם משיכה, im
meshicha, הגבהה, hagbaha, סודר. sudar. We can do it אגב קרקע. agav
karka. Yeah, well you could do is, I could say... or forget
that, I could say to Michael, "Michael, do a... well that's whether
כסף kesef is נקנה בחליפין nikne b'chalipin but whatever, but I could
say, "Michael, be, you know, give me your, your, you know, your
handkerchief. I'll take your handkerchief, by taking it I'm מקנה makne to
Charlie, you know, my car or whatever it is, you know, my
all of my gold bars or whatever, and then we could write
that up in a שטר, shtar, but the thing that effected the
קנין kinyan was the חליפין. chalipin. The שטר shtar doesn't effect a
קנין kinyan by מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay, so your point was that if
you wrote all that and then you tried to give it... The
what? No, no, my only point was to make it clear like
people might say, "Wait a minute, how why isn't the will just
a שטר מתנה?" shtar matana? So one is that the language is
different and makes it clear that you're just
gift... Right, right. The point here of רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan here
because here we actually dealing with an actual cash being given in
the will, okay, but it was if it was just done verbally
it would have been effective, but it was see the verbal instruction
was to write it and give it, and then he died before
it was able to be written and given. Okay, so that's one
more time. שכיב מרע שאמר כתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני ומת אין
כותבין ונותנין. Shichiv mera she-amar kitvu u-tnu mana le-ploni u-met, ein kotvin
ve-nosnin. שמא לא גמר להקנותו אלא בשטר Shema lo gamar le-haknoto ela
be-shtar ואין שטר לאחר מיתה. ve-ein shtar achar misa. Maybe he only
wanted it to be effective through the written, meaning did he say,
I want it to be effective now and I also would like
him to have the documentation? Then it would work even if it
hadn't been handed over. But maybe he meant I only want him
to have it by virtue of the mechanism of the written will,
and the written will would not be effective until it was handed
over. So therefore he says that we have to assume that, yeah,
it sort of sounds like a ספק, safek, but we can't give
it to him מספק mi-safek because maybe it was only the שטר
shtar that would have been the only mechanism to affect the gift.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר להו רבי אליעזר. Amar
lehu Rebbi Eliezer. So רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer said to the students
that were there, you know, and hearing this teaching of רבה בר
בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana in the name of רבי יוחנן,
Reb Yochanan, איזהרו בה. Izdaharu bah. Be careful to follow this. This
is a very important הלכה, halacha, you know, and pay attention to
this. Because you might think, oh he already gifted it verbally. No,
if he says write a שטר, shtar, we have to be concerned
that he only was gifting it or willing it via a שטר.
shtar. So רב שיזבי אמר רבי אליעזר אמרה. Rav Shizbi amar Rebbi
Eliezer amra. So that was one version. That it was said in
the name of רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan and רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
said, be careful with this הלכה. halacha. רב שיזבי, Rav Shizbi, a
different version. רבי אליעזר אמר, Rebbi Eliezer amar, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
said this teaching. דאמר להו רבי יוחנן, de-amar lehu Reb Yochanan, and
רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan who was actually there said, איזהרו בה, izdaharu
bah, be careful about this and keep this הלכה. halacha. Okay,
so which if רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan is sitting there, it's probably
taking place in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. Where was it said? This
was in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב, Rav, which probably was in
בבל, Bavel, so the setting might have been different. Anyway, okay. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, דוושתא דרב שיזבי
מסתברא. Duvshata de-Rav Shizbi mistabra. רב שיזבי'ס Rav Shizbi's version of the
events makes more sense. That רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer was the one
who said this rule and רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan said, be careful
with this, like pay attention to this. אי אמרת בשמי דרבי אליעזר
אמר. Ei amrat bishmei de-Rebbi Eliezer amar. If רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
said it, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer was a student of רבי יוחנן.
Reb Yochanan. So איצטריך רבי יוחנן לאסודי עליה דרבי אליעזר. Itzrich Reb
Yochanan le-asudei alei de-Rebbi Eliezer. So רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan has to
say,
look, you know, I mean,
true רבי אליעזר'ס Rebbi Eliezer's my תלמיד talmid or whatever, but I'm
telling everybody else like he's right, pay attention to him. Okay, he
needs my, you know, my הסכמה. haskama. But, okay. אלא אי אמרת
רבי יוחנן אמר. Ela ei amrat Reb Yochanan amar. But if רבי
יוחנן Reb Yochanan was the one who said it. איצטריך רבי אליעזר
לאסודי עליה דרבי יוחנן רבי? Itzrich Rebbi Eliezer le-asudei alei de-Reb Yochanan
rabi? Does רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer have to say, yeah, pay attention
to what the rabbi said, you know, he's right? So thank you
very much, I really needed your הסכמה. haskama. So anyway, okay. Anyway.
But the thing is an אמורא. Amora. That's what אמוראים Amoraim do,
right? Yeah, רבי יוחנן'ס Reb Yochanan's also an אמורא. Amora. But he's
not the language of איזהרו בה, izdaharu bah, like oh yeah, that's
a really important thing, right? You can tell it over but he
doesn't need his תלמיד'ס talmid's הסכמה. haskama. Sort of an interesting verb
to say, to like, yeah, he's right, like it's the verb of
testimony. What? לאסודי. le-asudei. Talking about שטרי, shtari, right? לאסודי. le-asudei. Ah,
לאסודי, le-asudei, that's interesting. To testify. Yeah, and in the context of
שטר, shtar, right? Talking about שטרות shtaros as evidence,
etc. Nice to use that word to say he's right. Yeah, that's
true, it's a great word. Yeah, no, איזהרו, izdaharu, but the גמרא
Gemara when it refers to what he did, it's לאסודי ביה le-asudei
beih to like testify on his behalf. Right, that was a nice
point. By the way, it's an interesting point in like כיבוד אב
ואם, kibbud av v'eim, right? You're not supposed to like contradict your
parent in public, but you also in many cases you're not supposed
to also agree with them in the sense that, in the context
in which they need your הסכמה, haskama, right? So like your father
says something and you say, yeah, you should listen to him, he's
right. Like, you know, that actually could be a פגיעה על הכבוד,
pegia al ha-kavod, you know, like what, he needs your הסכמה haskama
to tell people that he's right? You know? So anyway, so that's
like the issue being dealt with here. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ועוד. Ve-od. What? My kid says we agree with
each other, yeah אבא'ס Abba's right.
That's a little different than in public vis-a-vis others, you know, but
okay. ועוד תא שמע דרבי אליעזר אמרה. Ve-od, ta shema de-Rebbi Eliezer
amra. I'll prove to you רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer was the one
who said it and רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan was the one who
gave his הסכמה. haskama. דשלח רבין משמיה דרבי אבהו. De-shalach Ravin mishmei
de-Rebbi Abbahu. רבין Ravin sent from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel in the
name of רבי אבהו. Rebbi Abbahu. הוו יודעין, Hevei yodin, you should
be aware, all this being aware, דשלח רבי אליעזר לגולה. de-shalach Rebbi
Eliezer le-golah. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer sent to the exile, to בבל.
Bavel. משום רבינו. Mishum rabbeinu. In the name of our master. Now
the master here, although רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is a student of
רבי יוחנן, Reb Yochanan, he's also a student of רב. Rav. So
the רבינו rabbeinu in this context is רב. Rav. רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer sent in the name of רב, Rav, שכיב
מרע שאמר כתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני Shichiv mera she-amar kitvu u-tnu mana
le-ploni ומת אין כותבין ונותנין. u-met ein kotvin ve-nosnin. He said write
and hand over a will to so-and-so, you do not do it
after. And he dies and you haven't gotten around to it, you
cannot do it. שמא לא גמר להקנות אלא בשטר, Shema lo gamar
lehaknos ela bish'tar, maybe he only wanted to be effective through the
written will, ואין שטר אחר מיתה, ve'ein shtar achar misa, and that
is does not take effect after death. Rav Yochanan, for that was
what Rav Elazar was now the one who had announced that statement,
and he even said in the name of Rav.
רבי יוחנן אמר תיבדק, Rav Yochanan amar tibadek, and Rav Yochanan says,
yeah, but you have to, I agree with it, and here he's
sort of giving a הסכמה haskama to that teaching, but you have
to check the circumstances. So he's not disagreeing, he's just like qualifying.
What does it mean you have to check the circumstances? מאי תיבדק,
Mai tibadek, what does that mean? So כי אתא רב דימי אמר,
ki asa Rav Dimi amar, when Rav Dimi came from Eretz Yisrael,
all this teaching coming from Eretz Yisrael, he said, דיאתיקי מבטלת דיאתיקי.
deyateki mevateles deyateki. So he said two things. The first one is
not, I mean it's relevant to our larger topic, but not directly
to this case about when the שכיב מרע shchiv meira says כיתבו
ותנו. kisvu utnu. The first teaching was just a later will and
testament overrides an earlier will and testament. Okay, last will and testament
overrides an earlier will and testament. דיאתיקי מבטלת דיאתיקי. deyateki mevateles deyateki.
Okay, now let me just check there was one point in the
רשב"ם, Rashbam, one minute.
Okay, yeah, there's going to be a גמרא Gemara later on that's
going to ask is there a way to write a will that
if you did it with a קניין, kinyan, like with a סודר
sudar together with the will, can you then override that type of
a will and testament later? And it's a debate of אמוראים, Amora'im,
but we actually שמואל הכי פסקן-s Shmuel hakhi pasken you can, that
even a will and testament that came with a קניין, kinyan, okay,
because it's a context of a will and testament, you always retain
the right to override it and to write a later one and
to write a you know, until you die, right. Okay, so number
one is a later will and testament overrides an earlier one. דיאתיקי
מבטלת דיאתיקי. deyateki mevateles deyateki. And number two, our immediate topic. שכיב
מרע שאמר כיתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני ומת, shchiv meira she'amar kisvu utnu
maneh leploni umes, which is exactly our issue. So he says you're
right, it might be a problem, but you have to look at
the circumstances. רואין, Roeen, you assess the circumstances. אם כמייפה את כוחו,
Im kimeyafes es kocho, if it's clear from context that he wanted
the will written to give him extra sort of strength. Like obviously
I want my verbal statement to be the binding and to have
rights to it right now, or you know, this to be the
binding statement, and I also want him to have a document as
you know, documentary proof to it. But it's not that the document
is the vehicle for effecting it, my words are through the classic
verbal מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv meira plus write him a document.
If that's the context in which it's being said, כותבין, kosvin, then
you can write that document after death because the will took effect.
ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, but if it's not, and presumably meaning if
it's not clear that that's the case, because there's always going to
be the gray area where you don't know whether he meant this
or not. So if it's clear he meant it as an additional
proof then write it after death, but if it's vague and maybe
he didn't mean to give it unless it was with a document,
so אין כותבין, ein kosvin, then you can't write it. Okay, so
now how are we going to know? So if you just had
רבי יוחנן's Rav Yochanan statement was like there are no rules, you
have to look at the circumstances, right, and you have to assess
based on the circumstances. But that's hard, like הלכה halacha always likes
there to be clear rules. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes with this. So מתיב רבי אבא בר ממל. masiv Rebbe Abba
bar Memel. רבי אבא בר ממל Rebbe Abba bar Memel asked. בריא
שאמר כיתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני ומת, Bari she'amar kisvu utnu maneh leploni
umes, אין כותבין ונותנין. ein kosvin venosnin. We have a מימרא memra
that says that if a healthy person said, you know, write to
so-and-so and give it to him, you would not write it after
he died. By the way, that's it just occurred to me now
that's a little strange because it says מנה, maneh, so I don't
know how the מנה, maneh, which is cash, is supposed to operate
through a שטר. shtar. Okay, but maybe it means that you also
did a קניין kinyan for it or whatever. But anyway, if the
guy is healthy you assume that he did not want to finalize
the sale until the שטר shtar was handed over. When he uses
a שטר. shtar. אין כותבין Ein kosvin though, why can't you just,
because it means he's the guy's not entitled to it. Because he
wasn't קונה koneh it. Okay, so if I say write a שטר
shtar because I want to give someone a מנה לפלוני maneh leploni
then you can't write a שטר? shtar? No, and then he died,
ומת. umes. Okay, בריא. bari. He was בריא bari and then he
dropped dead. Meaning you can't write it afterwards, you have to write
it before. You can't write it after he's dead. הא שכיב מרע,
ha shchiv meira, the implication would be that in the case of
a guy on his deathbed, כותבין ונותנין, kosvin venosnin, you could always
write it. So meaning this is a challenge on everything that's been
said before. Even רבי יוחנן Rav Yochanan says like unless we're certain
he meant this as an additional strength you would not write. Here
it says the implication is you always would write it in a
case of a שכיב מרע. shchiv meira. You would always assume that
it was the verbal act was the binding sort of, you know,
will and the שטר shtar is just an additional thing. What does
that mean an additional thing? It's simply evidence. Evidence, yeah. Exactly. Exactly.
So הוא מתיב לה ומפרק לה, hu masiv la u'mefarek la, he
asked this and then he gave an
answer. במייפה את כוחו, Bimeyafes es kocho, which is
like a, now that
answer but you... As a way of giving him extra strength, as
a way of giving him evidence, but that the vehicle of the
will was the verbal one. So it doesn't mean that by a
שכיב מרע Shechiv Meira it always works. It means that by a
שכיב מרע Shechiv Meira you sometimes can write a שטר. Shtar. When
can you write a שטר? Shtar? When it's clear that you're doing
it as מיפות כוחו. Miyapes Kocho. Okay, there is like a literary
playfulness here, because מיפות כוחו Miyapes Kocho was the same thing as,
yeah he's right, he's right. You're being מיפה. Miyafe. That's a nice
point. Right, you know there is sort of a subtext to it.
Right. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I hear you. It's a nice point. היכי
דמי מיפות כוחו? Heichi Dami Miyapes Kocho? So what would now rather
than just saying we're going to assess it by every case, we're
going to have we need some rules. So how do you know
whether whether it means whether he's doing it as a שטר Shtar
in addition or the שטר Shtar should be the vehicle? כדאמר רב
חסדא וקנינא מיניה מוסיף אמתנתא דא. Kedamar Rav Chisda Ukanina Minei Mosif
Amatanata Da. Okay. So basically you write in the document,
okay, so this is so
we and we did a קנין Kinyan for him in addition to
this gift. So what was the case? The case was take a
look. Yeah, take a look at the רשב"ם. Rashbam. לקמן פרק מי
שמת אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל שכיב מרע שכתב כל נכסיו אף
על פי שקנו מידו הממון חוזר. Lekaman Perek Mi Shemet Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Shmuel Shechiv Meira Shekatav Kol Nechasav Af Al Pi Shekanu
Miyado Hamamon Chozer. Okay, so this by the way is another הלכה
Halacha about שכיב מרע. Shechiv Meira. The same way you can retract
it with another will and testament if you just get better. It's
automatic like if you don't die in this through this illness, eventually
we will all die, okay, but you actually recovered from this illness
that you thought you might die as a result of, it's automatically
the will is negated. So that's I mean whether well we'll see
about that. Okay. Wait, exactly when this is a negation. Okay, so
we'll see about all of this. Anyway, okay, and שמואל Shmuel said
that even if there was a קנין Kinyan in the מתנה, Matana,
since it was in the context of מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnat Shechiv
Meira, it is negated if the guy gets better. ומשמע הא מת
מקבל מתנה קנה ואף על פי שכתב קנין ובהא מתנת שכיב מרע
לא אמרינן שמא לא גמר להקנותו אלא בשטר ואין שטר לאחר מיתה.
Umashma Ha Met Mekabel Matana Kana Veaf Al Pi Shekatav Kinyan Uveha
Matnat Shechiv Meira Lo Amrinan Shema Lo Gamar Lehaknoto Ela Bishtar V'ein
Shtar Leachar Mita. Okay, so it's the same point. If you did
a קנין Kinyan but you didn't write the שטר, Shtar, should we
actually say that maybe like since the שטר Shtar didn't get
written the קנין Kinyan wouldn't be effective? ומקשינן מנהא התם לשמואל דאמר
מתנת שכיב מרע וכו'. Umakshinan Minah Hatam Leshmuel Deamar Matnat Shechiv Meira
V'chulei. Okay, okay, ומשני התם Umeshani Hatam
and in the last of the wide lines of the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
דמיפות כוחו הוא דרב יהודה אמר שמואל ואין הקנין מגרע כוח השטר
של שכיב מרע שלא הקנה אלא ליפות את כוחו. Demiyapes Kocho Hu
Derav Yehuda Amar Shmuel V'ein Hakinyan Megarea Koach Hashtar Shel Shechiv Meira
Shelo Hikna Ela Leyafes Et Kocho. Okay. So basically what he said
like this is sometimes,
okay I don't want to get into too much detail, probably shouldn't
have read that inside because I don't want to confuse you too
much. But the point is like this, right? It's similar to the
שטר. Shtar. A שטר Shtar or a קנין Kinyan like a קנין
סודר, Kinyan Sudar, right, can be seen as like oh it's more,
more is always better. But right, so maybe it's just done to
really show my real conviction, to give you documentary evidence. Fine. If
it's done in a way to be in addition to the effectiveness
of the מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnat Shechiv Meira, it works then it
can't hurt. But maybe by saying a שטר Shtar or doing a
קנין, Kinyan, I'm saying I don't want the verbal מתנת שכיב מרע
Matnat Shechiv Meira to work. I want this to work through a
קנין. Kinyan. I want this to work through a שטר. Shtar. And
if I'm doing that, then it's not necessarily better, because what if
those things didn't get done before I
died, you know because then it works on a different track which
might not be as effective as a מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnat Shechiv
Meira. So the question in all these cases is did you want
it in addition or did you want it instead? Okay. So there
רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel says, so again we'll
worry more about the specifics when we get to it. But כדאמר
רב חסדא וקנינא מיניה מוסיף אמתנתא דא. Kedamar Rav Chisda Ukanina Minei
Mosif Amatanata Da. And you actually wrote this in the
שטר. Shtar. Well it was commanded to be written in the שטר
Shtar or one of the other, I don't want to get into
the specifics of it, okay? But it was clear from the instruction
or from what was written in the שטר Shtar that what was
written in the שטר Shtar made it clear what the instruction was,
that the קנין Kinyan was meant as in
addition, not that the קנין Kinyan would be the vehicle. The קנין
Kinyan was in addition to the basic vehicle of the מתנת שכיב
מרע. Matnat Shechiv Meira. And you mean that you could go off
like if it was contested. Yeah, I mean we'll see about that
later. So it gets confusing. I don't want to hold up to
it. אבל הכי נמי דאמר אף כתובו וחתומו והבו ליה. Aval Hachi
Nami Deamar Af Kitvu Vechatumu Vehavu Lei. If you say אף, Af,
if you say I'm giving all my stuff to Michael and you
know what go ahead and even you should write him a שטר
Shtar for it. Okay. So when it's clear that I'm saying in
addition, like מוסיף אמתנתא דא, Mosif Amatanata Da, then that is not
the primary vehicle and therefore you can go ahead and write the
שטר לאחר מיתה. Shtar Leachar Mita. Okay. איתמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
הלכה כותבין ונותנין וכן אמר רבה אמר רב נחמן הלכה כותבין. Itmar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel Halacha Kotvin Venotnin Vechen Amar Rabba Amar Rav
Nachman Halacha Kotvin. You go ahead
and you write it. Now, does that mean in all cases? Are
they rejecting the qualifications we said before? You could read it that
way, but the רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't want to think that the גמרא
Gemara is making a radical departure after it laid out this whole
approach, so he says no, no, no. They mean in a case
where it's clear that you're מייפה כחו, meyafes kocho, that the primary
vehicle is the verbal מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv mei-ra, not the
written will, then you could write the will after death. Okay, so
the irony about all of this is the more you're trying to
move onto a track of classic קניינים, kinyanim, the more you might
be restricted by that track of classic קניינים. kinyanim. It doesn't always
make things better. Okay? It restricts you maybe more to those rules.
You, and a normal שטר shtar only works when you hand it
over, and a normal קניין kinyan only, you know, works under certain
circumstances. So if you're going to want something to have the effectiveness
of a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mei-ra and you want to
also do these extra things, make it clear that these things are
just extra, they're not the primary vehicle. Okay, so one more time,
a written will still is a חידוש. chiddush. It's not a שטר
מתנה. shtar matana. It works on מטלטלין. metaltelin. You're not saying you're
giving it now, you're saying this is what you want to happen
when you die, etc. Okay, that is like a written מתנת שכיב
מרע. matnas shchiv mei-ra. And that works, but only, it's only effective
and binding once it's handed over. That's point number one. You could
do a מתנת בריא matnas bari which is like a מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnas shchiv mei-ra, מהיום ולאחר מיתה, me-hayom u-le'achar misa, or a
minute before I die, make it explicit that you want the right
to retract it and so on. And then the question would be
if you gave a verbal מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mei-ra with
a command to be to write it, you have to decide whether
the basic vehicle is the verbal and the writing is an addition.
So if you're clear about that, great. Otherwise, we might think that
the basic vehicle is the written will and then it would have
to be written and executed and handed over while you're still alive.
Okay, so that's that. Was there a question? No? Okay, moving on
to the next משנה. Mishnah.
הכותב נכסיו לבנו. Ha-kosev nechasav le-vno. Now, we're actually going to deal
with, we're going to switch gears a bit because we talked about
a potential structure of מהיום ולאחר מיתה me-hayom u-le'achar misa as a
way of creating a type of a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv
mei-ra. We're going to talk about that structure even not in the
context of a will. Just may, or maybe it is, maybe it
isn't, but it doesn't really matter. We're just going to talk about
what's going to happen if somebody actually does that. Gift to his
son property, transfers the title now, and the פירות peiros will be
לאחר מיתה. le-achar misa. Okay. הכותב נכסיו לבניו
צריך שיכתוב מהיום ולאחר מיתה. Ha-kosev nechasav le-vanav tzarich she-yichtov me-hayom u-le'achar
misa Okay, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says this is not in the
context of a will, or it certainly doesn't have to be. What
would be another reason why you would want to do this if
not in the context of the will? So let's take a look
at the רשב"ם. Rashbam. He says הכותב נכסיו לבניו. Ha-kosev nechasav le-vanav
He says בריא שרוצה לישא אשה bari she-rotze lisa isha ואינו רוצה
לשעבד נכסיו לאשתו ve-eino rotze leshabed nechasav le-ishto פן ישיאו הבנים שיש
לו מאשה ראשונה. pen yasi'u habanim she-yesh lo mi-isha rishona. So he
has kids from a first wife and he doesn't want this woman
he's about to marry, he wants to make sure that like all
the property I have now, I want to go to my children
that I currently have. Okay, so if I get married and with
a second wife have more kids, they're going to have a piece
of the inheritance of what, of the property I have now. I'm
happy for them to have property I earn later but not the
property I have now. So I want to write all that property,
protect it from the kids I might have with this second wife.
Or maybe I would even want it protected from my second wife.
I don't want the כתובה, kesuvah, you know, to have liens on
this property. So before I get married, I'm going to transfer the
title to my kids. So then the, and then I get married,
then I have no property in my name, then she won't have
liens on that property. Okay, but even though I want to protect
the property, I don't want to give up the income from it
while I'm still alive. So what I do is I give them
the title and I've protected it now from my future kids inheriting
it and from my wife, my second wife having liens, but I
continue to get all of the benefit from it while I'm still
alive. What's that called when you don't own something but you, I
don't know, there's some, there's some term. Okay, I don't know. And
she does she continue to receive benefits in the way to have
any lien on that benefit? Yeah, if he earns new money and
gets new property, then she'd have a lien on those, those properties,
and he's receiving the benefit of those properties,
does she have any right? Oh, I guess it's true, meaning if
he goes ahead and he sells the fruit from that property and
puts it in his bank account, then she has right to seize
that money from that. But yeah, that's true. Okay.
הכותב נכסיו לבניו ha-kosev nechasav le-vanav. צריך שיכתוב מהיום ולאחר מיתה tzarich
she-yichtov me-hayom u-le'achar misa. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So if
you wanted to go ahead and do this, so the way to
do it is you write מהיום ולאחר מיתה, me-hayom u-le'achar misa, which
effectively does this. It protects the principal and it lets you to
continue benefits from it. רבי יוסי אומר אינו צריך. Rabbi Yossi omer
eino tzarich. No, even without writing it, it works. Now, according to
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, we're going to see what you basically said
wrote was this should be
yours לאחר מיתה. le-achar misa. So... So even if you wanted to
say מהיום ולאחר מיתה, mehayom v'leachar misa, you don't have to say
the word מהיום. mehayom. That's implicit.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, and we'll see that that's based on the גמרא.
Gemara. הכותב נכסיו לבנו לאחר מותו. Hakosev nechasav livno leachar moso. Now,
let's say you actually did this. It was a type of מהיום
ולאחר מיתה. mehayom v'leachar misa. האב אינו יכול למכור מפני שהם כתובים
לבן. Ha'av eino yachol limkor mipnei sheheim kesuvim laben. The father can't
sell the principal because the son right now owns the principal. והבן
אינו יכול למכור. Vehaben eino yachol limkor. This was not a case
of a where you had a right to retract. This was not
done in the context of a trying to be like a מתנת
שכיב מרע. matnas shichiv mera. This was a straight protecting my assets.
So you no longer have title, you can't sell. והבן אינו יכול
למכור מפני שהם ברשות האב. Vehaben eino yachol limkor mipnei sheheim birshus
ha'av. But the son can't sell because the father has control, at
least gets the benefit of the fruit. So he's meaning there's a
difference, notice the difference of the language. By the son it says
כתובים לבן kesuvim laben and by the father it says רשות האב.
rishus ha'av. So the father is the one who's control it's under
in the sense that he benefits from it, whereas the son is
the one who's entitled to it. He's going to get the title
to it, or he has the title to it. Is that like
the husband who gets the פירות peiros of the wife's property? He
can't sell and she can't... can't he sell a piece of that
property? Right, so that has so yes, that is another classic example
of one person having the title and the other having the פירות.
peiros. And there's questions about can anybody do something, and there's whole
תקנת אושא Takanas Usha that prevents, you know, certain things from happening.
So yes, it's a very parallel situation. Let's finish the משנה. Mishna.
I actually was going to ask. Okay, so yes, it definitely is
a parallel. You also you'll get credit too on your final grade.
Okay. מכר האב, מכורים עד שימות. Machar ha'av, mechurin ad sheyamus. Now,
it doesn't mean that you can't sell at all. Why can't you
at least sell what you own? So if the father sells his
right to the פירות, peiros, he can sell his right to the
פירות, peiros, and he can transfer that and somebody else will get
the פירות peiros until the father dies, right? You can't sell more
than you own. So if I now am retaining the right to
the fruit until I die, I can sell the right to the
fruit from this land, you know, or the right to the income.
Fruit doesn't have to literally mean fruit. It could be like a
rental property, you know, the right to the income from this land
until I die, and but once, you know, I die, then you
don't get it anymore. מכר הבן, אין ללוקח בהם כלום עד שימות
האב. Machar haben, ein lalokeiach bahem klum ad sheyamus ha'av.
Let's say the son sells the title. Great, so now you own
the title. You bought the title from the son. Can you do
anything with that title? No. Okay, because the father still has control
over it. Once the father dies, now you fully own the piece
of land because the son sold everything he had. He had the
title with no rights until the father died and the title with
full rights once the father died. So that's what he sold to
you and that's where you would get the benefit and use of
it once the father died. Now of course the question is can
you then sell your title? Meaning how much, you know, can you
do with the title even without the rights? We'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. First we're going to focus on רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכי כתב מהיום ולאחר מיתה
מאי הוי? V'chi kasav mehayom v'leachar misa mai havay? Oh, well first
actually we're going to focus on the basic structure of מהיום ולאחר
מיתה. mehayom v'leachar misa. How does מהיום ולאחר מיתה mehayom v'leachar misa
work? Why does this work at all? הא תנן, Ha tenan, we
taught by גיטין, Gittin, מהיום ולאחר מיתה mehayom v'leachar misa גט ואינו
גט. get ve'eino get. If a guy gives a גט get to
his wife and he says it should take effect as of today
and after I die. Okay, now presumably again the reason he's trying
to say that is maybe he only wants it, you know, what
he really is trying to say is it should take effect today
if and when I die. Okay, and the reason presumably is he
wants to save his wife from יבום yibum would be an example.
So what he really means is a classic example would be he'd
be on his deathbed and he would say let this be as
effective as of today if I die from this חולי. choli. You
know, if I and okay now if he said that, that would
be great. That's exactly what he's trying to say. Or he takes
a trip. Or he takes a trip, exactly, goes off to war,
if I don't return, let it be effective as of today. So
if you say that explicitly, great. But you didn't say it explicitly.
What you said is מהיום ולאחר מיתה. mehayom v'leachar misa. This is
effective as of today and when I die and after I die.
So does it work or not work? Did you mean for it
to be effective today if you die and you don't come back,
or do you mean that
it should finish being effective after you're dead? It can't finish being
effective after you're dead. So the הלכה halacha is
so it says גט ואינו גט, get ve'eino get, we don't know
if it's a גט get or not, we don't know how to
parse those words. ואם מת, חולצת ולא מתייבמת. V'im meis, choletzes v'lo
misyabemes. And if the guy dies, the woman has to do חליצה
chalitza because maybe she wasn't divorced and therefore she's חייב chayav to
do חליצה. chalitza. But she can't do יבום yibum because maybe she
was divorced. And if she's divorced, you do יבום yibum that's an
איסור עריות, issur arayos, it's a brother's, you know, brother's wife, even
divorced wife. Okay, so she's ספק מגורשת. safek megureshes. So how come...
There she's ספק מגורשת. safek megureshes. Why don't we say here it's
a ספק מתנה? safek matanah?
Right? Same thing. So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם מספקא לן
אי תנאה הוי אי חזרה הוי. hasam mesapka lan ee tnaa havy
ee chazara havy. There we don't know how to read it. Is
he saying it's effective as of today if I die, if I
don't return, or maybe he's retracting himself? It's effective as of today.
No, no, no, it's effective after I die. It's a little funny
to read it that way, you know, you could say it's effective
partly today and finishes being effective after I die, but either way
it wouldn't work. If some part of what you wanted to be
effective by a גט get is after you die, it's too late
to be effective. Okay, so if
so, that would not work if it did not mean תנאי, tnai,
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but here we have a very good way
to parse it. Okay הכא, hacha, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka'amar lay.
We can literally say partly today and partly after you die, there's
a direct way to translate that. גופא קני מהיום, gufa kani me-hayom,
the title you own today, you're transferring today. פירא לאחר מיתה pera
le-achar misa and the income from it and the benefit of it
that's transferred after death. So that works totally and it's a straight
parsing of the words and therefore this is easy to understand the
effectiveness of this phrase in a דיני ממונות dinei mammonos case.
In the case of a גט, get, you said מהיום ולאחר מיתה,
me-hayom le-achar misa, if you translate that as you're divorced from
me today in the event that I die, yes that's precisely the
formulation that's not good, right? No, that's precisely the formulation that is
good. That's what I'm trying to figure out because the מיתה misa
is what
finalizes, but it's just a condition being met. Not when I die.
In the event that means under the circumstances that. Yeah, so if
I say it at ten o'clock in the morning and the person
dies at eleven o'clock, למפרע le-mafrei'a she was... Exactly. Exactly. Yep. Yeah,
that's the other thing, it took effect from מעכשיו. me-achshav. Right. Right.
Okay, now רב יוסף אמר אינו צריך. Rav Yosef amar ein tzarich.
So now we're רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
you don't have to say this phrase, but what it really means
is you don't have to say the מהיום me-hayom part of the
phrase. Even if you just said לאחר מיתה, le-achar misa, we're going
to interpret it to be מהיום ולאחר מיתה. me-hayom le-achar misa.
So רבה בר אבוה, Rabba bar Avuha, רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar
Avuha חלש. chulash. He fell ill. Of course in a context of
שכיב מרע shechiv mera people falling ill, right? You know what, okay,
it's you know always often in the גמרא Gemara when somebody is
חלש cholash and people come to visit him, there's often a sense
like you know he might die as a result. I mean they
did not, the medical profession wasn't what it was today.
Okay, חלש. chulash. על גבי רב הונא ורב נחמן. al gabay Rav
Huna ve-Rav Nachman. So רב הונא Rav Huna and רב נחמן Rav
Nachman came to visit him.
אמר ליה רב הונא לרב נחמן, amar lay Rav Huna le-Rav Nachman,
בעי מיניה הלכה כרב יוסף או אין הלכה כרב יוסף? bo minei
halacha ke-Rav Yosef oy ein halacha ke-Rav Yosef? Go ask him if
we פסקנ pasken like רב יוסף Rav Yosef or not. I know,
he's dying, so we need to learn know some הלכה, halacha, we
need some פסק, psak, we need to get some of his תורה
Torah before he dies. Okay, it also could be a subtle way
of hinting to him, hey buddy, you might want to write a
will now that you're... I'm serious. Maybe that's also, you know, רב
יוסף מהיום ולאחר מיתה, Rav Yosef me-hayom le-achar misa, maybe the guy
will say, maybe it's like a good subtle way to urge him
to give, you know, to start handling his affairs. Anyway, he said
go ask him if we rule like רב יוסף Rav Yosef or
not. אמר ליה, amar lay, he said back to him, טעמא דרב
יוסף לא ידענא, הלכה איבעי מיניה? ta'ama de-Rav Yosef lo yadana, halacha
i-bayi minei? I don't even understand what רב יוסף Rav Yosef's position
is based on, that you don't have to write מהיום. me-hayom. I'm
going to go ask him how we פסקנ? pasken? Like, you know,
you don't ask out of ignorance, you want to understand what the
issues are before you ask a question. ואמר ליה, va-amar lay, את
בעי מיניה אי הלכה אי לאו. at bayi minei i-halacha i-lav. You
go ask him if that's how we rule. וטעמא אנא אמינא לך,
ve-ta'ama ana amina lach, and I'll tell you what the reasoning is.
Okay, we'll worry about the reasoning later, you go ask him. Why
he couldn't ask him himself I don't know, maybe it had to
do, well in private I guess. Maybe it had to do with
what the relationship was like, you know, who would more get an
answer. Anyway, בעי מיניה, bayi minei, he asked him, how do we
rule? אמר ליה, amar lay, so רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha
said to him, הכי אמר רב, hachi amar Rav, this is what
we say in the name of רב, Rav, הלכה כרב יוסף. halacha
ke-Rav Yosef. We rule like רב יוסף Rav Yosef even if you
don't say
מהיום. me-hayom. פשט ונפק, pashat ve-nafak, then they left. So אמר ליה,
amar lay, so אמר ליה, amar lay, so he I forget who's
talking anyway, but the one who said go ask and said, היינו
טעמא דרב יוסף. hainu ta'ama de-Rav Yosef. Good, and we פסקנ pasken
like him. Now let me tell you what the reasoning is based
on. Here's his reasoning. דאמר זמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו. de-amar zmano
shel shtar mochi'ach alav. The date in the שטר shtar testifies on
itself, it makes itself evident. Why are you dating a document? If
the document is saying לאחר מיתה, le-achar misa, there's no need to
date it because the whole effectiveness is when the guy dies. So
why would you date it? The only reason you would date it
would be to say that it should take effect as of today.
The date is an implicit statement of the מהיום. me-hayom. Okay, so
that is this position. Now there's a very interesting thing because this
also gets discussed by a גט. get. Okay, if somebody writes in
a גט, get, זה גיטך אם מתי. zeh gittich im masi. This
will be your גט get if I die. As you say literally
if. Now but if you say מהיום אם מתי, me-hayom im masi,
then that's very clear, takes effect today on the in the circumstances
of my death. If you just said if I die, maybe that
means without the מהיום, me-hayom, maybe that means if and when I
die. Okay, so how you read the אם מתי im masi without
the מהיום... me-hayom... מהיום. mehayom. So רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi says, oh,
no problem, if there's a date in the שטר shtar then it's
like you said מהיום. mehayom. Okay, so the responsa has a whole
discussion of maybe do we פסקן paskin the same way by a
שטר מתנה shtar matana as we do by a גט? get? Right,
there could be a lot of different considerations, the weight of the
issue, you know, other types of like the גמרא Gemara before said
different ways of parsing things. Okay, but anyway, this גמרא Gemara seems
to say that at least by a שטר מתנה, shtar matana, I
mean at least by a שטר shtar of קנין kinyan like of
property, okay, we go like רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi and we say
the date indicates that it means as of today or else why
would you need a date if it's only going to be effective
when the guy dies? Okay, yes. Isn't there a general rule that
we follow רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi in disputes with רבי
יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda?
Yeah, maybe.
So yeah, I mean but we are פסקן. paskin. You mean why
do we have to ask the question? Why even ask, yeah. I
mean the logic might be, yeah, there's other גמרות Gemaras about it
and by גטין Gittin and so on. So okay, this is not
the only piece of evidence. All right, so the משנה Mishnah says
like this, תני נמי הכי, tani nami hachi, רבי יוסי אומר Rebbi
Yossi omer אינו צריך מפני שזמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו. eino tzarich
mipnei she-zmano shel shtar mochiach alav. Look at that. There's an explicit
ברייתא Beraita that gave the reason. The date of the שטר shtar
testifies on itself that you mean it's effective as of today. בעי
מיני רבא מרב נחמן ba'ei minei Rava me-Rav Nachman בהקנאה מהו? be-hakna
mahu?
Now,
this seems to be saying, okay, not like we get that you're
פסקן paskin like רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi, but let's put that aside.
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda debate. Are they
debating a, you know, are they debating just in a normal שטר
shtar or would they even debate in a שטר shtar that you
did a קנין kinyan in the שטר? shtar? Okay, we discussed that
before. So the שטר shtar could say like,
you know, Dov told us did a קנין kinyan with the עדים
edim and he said that he's transferring his property, you know, to
Eli there לאחר מיתה. l'achar misa. Okay, so it just said לאחר
מיתה, l'achar misa, it didn't say מהיום, mehayom, but it said he
did a קנין kinyan with us right today, right? So do we
interpret the קנין kinyan as being effectively saying מהיום? mehayom?
Okay, so maybe, you know, there's no, so רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi
says we always interpret the date as saying מהיום mehayom and the
רבנן Rabbanan disagree, but maybe the רבנן Rabbanan wouldn't disagree or רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda wouldn't disagree if there was a קנין kinyan in
the שטר. shtar. The קנין kinyan might effectively be a way of
saying מהיום. mehayom. So that was the question. Okay, so where were
we?
בהקנאה מהו? be-hakna mahu? How about when there's a קנין kinyan in
the שטר? shtar? Will that be an effective way of saying
מהיום? mehayom? Wait, Rabbi, do you mean a קנין kinyan in the
שטר? shtar? You mean the שטר shtar testifies to the fact that
the person who was dictating the שטר shtar said, did a קנין
kinyan with the עדים. edim. Like you know what the כתובה kesubah
says? What does the end of the כתובה kesubah say when the
rabbi adds the little thing? וקנינא מיניה, vekoninu minei, right, על כל
מה דכתיב ומפורש לעיל. al kol mah de-kasiv u-meforaish le'eil. That's evidence,
testimony that the קנין kinyan was done. Right? It's not effecting the
קנין. kinyan. Correct, it's testimony. And normally the קנין kinyan is done
with the עדים. edim. Right? The עדים edim basically, the שטר shtar
is normally in the words of the עדים edim like a number
of שטרות, shtaros, a classic שטר. shtar. It's funny we don't do
this in our כתובה kesubah but some כתובות kesubahs actually begin with
the following:
אנן סהדי איך, anan sa'adei eich, we testify to the fact that,
you know,
באחד בשבת be-chad be-shabbas blah blah blah blah blah. So we the
witnesses are testifying to the following fact and we the witnesses did
a קנין kinyan with the husband on all of this and then
they sign their names to it. So it's basically like the verbalized
testimony words of the witnesses. So this is a קנין שכתוב בשטר.
kinyan she-kasuv bi-shtar. Okay, now,
so that's the question. If the שטר shtar actually explicitly said he
did a קנין kinyan with us, he didn't just hand over the
שטר, shtar, because you can hand over the שטר, shtar, the שטר
shtar could be the vehicle, right? This is a שטר מתנה, shtar
matana, not a שטר שכיב מרע, shtar shechiv mera, a שטר מתנה,
shtar matana, but in addition to the שטר shtar being the vehicle
and the handing over the שטר shtar in a שטר קנין shtar
kinyan by this piece of land, it actually says that you did
a קנין. kinyan. Will the fact that it says you did a
קנין kinyan and that's written in the שטר shtar be interpreted to
mean מהיום mehayom even if it didn't have the words מהיום? mehayom?
Okay, so he says בהקנאה מהו? be-hakna mahu? אמר ליה בהקנאה אינו
צריך. amar lei be-hakna eino tzarich. Yeah, by הקנאה hakna'a you don't
have to say מהיום. mehayom. Okay, רב פפא אמר איכא אקנאתא דצריך
ואיכא אקנאתא דלא צריך. Rav Pappa amar ika akna'ata de-tzarich ve-ika akna'ata
de-lo tzarich. It depends, depends on how it's phrased. Sometimes you need
it, sometimes you don't need it.
אקנייה וקנינא
מיניה, akneiyei ve-kanina minei, לא צריך. lo tzarich. If
it said the person said to us be קונה koneh for
so-and-so and then at the end of the שטר shtar said and
we were קונה koneh for so-and-so. In that case, because of the
double language of קנין, kinyan, it's showing that you meant מהיום. mehayom.
Okay, if you said in the beginning אקנייה, akneiyei, he told us
to be קונה koneh for ראובן Reuven and we were קונה koneh
for ראובן. Reuven. But קנינא מיניה ואקנייה, kanina minei ve-akneiyei, if in
the beginning of the שטר shtar it says We were קונה koneh
for ראובן Reuven this field לאחר מיתה, leachar misa, da da da
da da, and the guy told us to be קונה koneh for
ראובן, Reuven, so in that case, צריך, tzarich, that's not, doesn't show
that an extra sense of giving it to him and it's not
effective. What's the difference of the order? So the רשבם Rashbam says
the difference is is that one sort of seems to be like
clarifying and the other seems to be repeating. Meaning if you said:
"We were קונה koneh for him," and then at the end you
said, "and because the guy said to be קונה," koneh, you're clarifying
what we did. Why were we קונה koneh for him? Oh he
told us to be קונה. koneh. So it's really only making like
one statement that we were קונה koneh for this person, so it
doesn't necessarily mean that extra oomph and to be saying it means
מעכשיו. meachshav. So we can't read the מעכשיו meachshav into the שטר.
shtar. If however it said:
"He told us to be קונה," koneh, right, then you don't really
have to say and we did it. If you're saying "He told
us to be קונה" koneh and you're signing your names, it's like
implicit that you did it. So if you say he told us
to be קונה koneh and then you say and we were קונה,
koneh, so that seems like a little redundant. So we're going to
read that little redundancy as extra sort of indicating something extra was
going on here and that you meant for it to be effective
as of today. Okay, it seems like a lot of hair splitting,
which is believe it or not what the גמרא Gemara actually asks
right now. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: מתקיף
לה רב חנינא מסורא. Maskif la Rav Chanina miSura. רב חנינא מסורא
Rav Chanina miSura asks from this: מי איכא מידי דאנן לא ידעינן
וספרא ידעי? Mi ika midi deanan lo yadinan vesafra yadi? Is there
anything like we wouldn't know to parse a difference between קנינא ואקני
kanina veaknei and אקני וקנינא? aknei vekanina? You go to the בית
מדרש Beis Medrash and you ask and they'll say, "I don't know,
should that make a difference?" Like nobody would know that that would
be a meaningful difference. And you think the scribes know that it
makes a difference? Meaning the only reason the language could make a
difference in the שטר shtar is if it reflected a real difference
about what was going on, right? If it was just like two
versions of the same, if the scribes didn't give any weight to
whether it was framed this way or that way, right, it couldn't
mean anything. It must mean that the people that are actually writing
the documents know that this terminology one way means one thing and
one way means another thing. So how's that possible that the scribes
have a certain meaning when they phrase it this way and not
that and we here in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash are completely
ignorant of it? So it says so it must be that you're
just making this up. This doesn't really mean anything. שלחו לספרא דאביי.
Shalchu lesafra deAbaye. So they went and asked אביי's Abaye scribes: "Hey,
does it make any difference how you frame it this way or
that way? Is it just a stylistic thing?" ידעי. Yadi. And yeah,
they knew. They said: "No, this way it means he means it
to be effective as of today and this way he doesn't mean
it." וספרא דרבא ידעי. Vesafra deRava yadi.
And they went and asked רבא's Rava scribes and they also knew
that there was a difference. So guess what, rabbis, you don't always
know people's technical fields, right? These scribes, it's their expertise, it's their
technical field. You sometimes, you know that's why like judges sometimes, like
a judge for patent cases, right, like you know you need an
enormous amount of technical knowledge where just because you're the judge doesn't
mean you're an expert in that field. So you as the judge
have to parse a שטר, shtar, but it doesn't mean you always
know exactly what the scribes are getting at by slightly different languages.
Okay, so that's pretty fascinating. Okay, so רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua, let's just get to the two dots
here. אמר: בין אקני וקנינא מיניה בין קנינא מיניה ואקני לא צריך.
Amar: bein aknei vekanina minei bein kanina minei veaknei lo tzarich. You
know what? Either way, it's a double language and it means extra
sort of oomph. Whichever way you say it, if the קנין kinyan
is written in the שטר, shtar, then you do then what do
you call it? Then we read it to mean מעכשיו meachshav and
there's no debate and we read it to mean
מעכשיו. meachshav. ובדוכרן פתגמי דהוי באנפנא פליגי. Uveduchran pisgamei dehavi beanpana pligi.
The debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
is when the שטר shtar doesn't say a קנין. kinyan. The שטר
shtar just says like we are, it's not saying we did a
קנין kinyan for the person. It just said: "No, we are testifying
that we saw that ראובן Reuven basically gave to שמעון, Shimon, you
know his קרקע לאחר מיתה." karka leachar misa. So it's not saying
that we the עדים eidin did a קנין. kinyan. Do you understand
the difference is בדוכרן פתגמי דהוי באנפנא beduchran pisgamei dehavi beanpana means
we are recording things that we have seen. We saw that ראובן
Reuven you know did a קנין סודר kinyan sudar with שמעון Shimon
and said it should be effective לאחר מיתה. leachar misa. Okay, that
would be a case where it where it where it you're not
saying מעכשיו meachshav and it's the debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, that's but if the שטר shtar
says we the עדים eidin did a קנין kinyan on behalf of
the recipient so and you have that double language however that double
language appears whatever order it's to be interpreted to mean מעכשיו. meachshav.
אמר רב כהנא: אמריתי לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד מנהרדעא. Amar Rav Kahana:
amrisi lishmaysei kamei deRav Zevid miNehardea. I said this in front of
רב זביד מנהרדעא Rav Zevid miNehardea and ואמרי לה: אסון הכי מתניתון
לן יותי. veamrei lah: asun hachi masnisun lan yuti. That way that
it was a question and then I tell you there were different
versions. אנן הכי מתנינן לה. Anan hachi masninan lah. Here is how
we teach it. אמר רבא אמר רב נחמן: באקנוי אינו צריך. Amar
Rava amar Rav Nachman: beaknoi eino tzarich. If it's a שטר קנין
shtar kinyan you do not need meaning there's no debate. It always
means מעכשיו. meachshav. בין אקני וקנינא מיניה בין קנינא מיניה ואקני. Bein
aknei vekanina minei bein kanina minei veaknei. Whatever order it is, if
it's a שטר קנין shtar kinyan it always... Which means מהיום mehayaum
and there's no debate.
לא צריך. lo tzorich. בדוכתין פיתגמי דהוו באנא beduchtin pitgamei dehavu beana
when they're just saying we are recording things that we have seen
but we were not directly party to doing a קנין kinyan then
פליגי pligi that's the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi if it doesn't say מהיום mehayaum do we read
it to mean מהיום mehayaum because of the date or do we
not